We continue here on דף ל"ג עמוד א', Daf Lamed Gimmel Amud
Aleph, middle of the page, 33a,
and we are dealing with where you do various insertions: משיב הרוח,
Mashiv HaRuach, ותן טל ומטר, V'ten Tal U'matar, הבדלה Havdalah where you
put in חונן הדעת Chonen HaDa'at because it's the beginning of the
ברכות brachot of חול chol and because it's related to the ישועת
דעת, Yeshuat Da'at, and now on that focus about the importance of
דעת da'at we pick up about five lines before the lines get
wide. אמר רבי אמי, Amar Rabbi Ami, excuse me, six lines before,
אמר רבי אמי: Amar Rabbi Ami: גדולה דעה. Gedolah De'ah. Line starts
with word מתוך. Mitoch. So אמר רבי אמי: Amar Rabbi Ami: גדולה
דעה שניתנה בתחילת ברכה של חול. Gedolah De'ah shenitnah bitchilat bracha shel
chol. So oh great is intellect that it was the very first
ברכה bracha of the weekday, that the very first thing that we
need in order to live a responsible life and to live a
life of meaning is the intellect. So therefore before you know תשובה
teshuvah and סליחה selichah and all those things, that's only meaningful once
we can start assessing and thinking about our lives. So that is
the very first of the ברכות, brachot, the very most fundamental thing
that we first have to ask for God. ואמר רבי אמי, V'amar
Rabbi Ami, and said Rabbi Ami: גדולה דעה שניתנה בין שתי אותיות.
Gedolah De'ah shenitnah bein shtei otiyot. Great is intellect, knowledge, that it's
placed between two of God's names. שנאמר כי אל דעות ה'. Shene'emar
Ki El de'ot Hashem. A God of knowledge, wisdom, is God. So
the fact that it appears before God's name, before and after, shows
how central and important this is. וכל מי שאין בו דעה, V'chol
mi she'ein bo de'ah, making a little bit of an extreme statement
now, whoever lacks basic intellect, אסור לרחם עליו, assur l'rachem alav, you
can't have compassion for him, שנאמר כי לא עם בינות הוא, shene'emar
Ki lo am binot hu, they are not a people of understanding,
על כן לא ירחמנו עושהו, al ken lo yerachamenu osehu, therefore their
Creator will not have compassion on them. Now one hopes that this
does not mean that somebody
that is not born with certain intellectual capacities. Obviously those are the
people that most need our רחמים, rachamim, our compassion, in order to
make sure that they are protected and not taken advantage of and
provided for and so on. But it presumably it means somebody that
chooses to go not to like the case in the פסוק pasuk
כי לא עם בינות הוא, Ki lo am binot hu, does not
mean that we don't have intellect as a people, but if we
act in ways which are just not being responsible and not being
thoughtful, then in a way there's almost like the well you get
what's coming to you type of
sense. So, in a way it seems a little harsh, but in
another way it's a statement about human responsibility because if you're bringing
troubles upon yourself and acting in irresponsible ways, in ways that reflects
you're not thinking about
things, so maybe you need to learn from that. So it's like
think about parenting, that sometimes you let your kids learn from their
mistakes as a way of learning about how to be responsible. So
I would think that that's the sense here of this statement.
Why do you
say that
it's not harsh? Well, it's my attempt, it's my attempt to read
it in a little harsh way.
It's very terrible.
I disagree.
There are people who
seem to have intelligence who refuse to
acknowledge...
No, no, no, I think Rifka's upset because she thinks it means
even somebody that is born congenitally without the ability to be... I
would never think that.
But in
the context of the פסוק pasuk כי לא עם בינות הוא, Ki
lo am binot hu, it does not mean people that really don't
have the capacity to think. It means people that are not being
thoughtful in their lives, that are not using their intellect.
Okay, it requires an addition here. I
understand.
What you're saying is it's not כל מי שאין בו דעה, kol
mi she'ein bo de'ah, it could be כל מי שאינו לא חי
חיים של דעה kol mi she'eino lo chai chayei shel de'ah or
somebody's... Right, whatever. I understand. I understand, but I do think it
is not a stretch given the פסוק pasuk that is quoted. But
the
מהרש"א Maharsha says... מהרש"א, Maharsha, well right.
I think
he maintains as fundamental
as it deserves compassion one
without knowledge is based on the word... Right. All right. אמר רבי
אלעזר: Amar Rabbi Eleazar: גדולה מקדש.
Gedolah
Mikdash.
Now that we're on this theme about things that are between God's
names, great is the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash שניתן בין שתי אותיות
shenitan bein shtei otiyot that it appears between two names of God.
שנאמר פעלת ה' מקדש ה'. Shene'emar Pa'alta Hashem Mikdash Hashem.
You have fashioned God, your sanctuary, oh God. So Hashem, Mikdash, Hashem,
it is great is between those two names of God. ואמר רבי
אלעזר: V'amar Rabbi Eleazar: כל אדם שיש בו דעה, kol adam sheyesh
bo de'ah, כאילו נבנה בית המקדש בימיו. ke'ilu nivneh Beit HaMikdash b'yamav.
Now we're going to connect the statement earlier statement about intellect with
this statement about the מקדש Mikdash and if you have intellect or
presumably you use your intellect, you see, and by the way Rifka
here, כל מי שיש בו דעה, kol mi sheyesh bo de'ah, presumably
means you use your intellect, it doesn't mean that anybody that's born
with intelligence is like the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is built. Inherently?
No, but presumably let's see just based
on דעה נתנה בין שתי אותיות, de'ah nitnah bein shtei osiyos, מקדש
נתנה בין שתי אותיות, mikdash nitnah bein shtei osiyos,
the intellect is between two words of God, two names of God,
and so is the מקדש. Mikdash. So again, it doesn't mean what
are you—I mean, to interpret this as anybody that's just born with
intelligence is like the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was built, seems like
a nonsensical statement. I think from context, יש בו דעה yesh bo
de'ah means uses your intellect in your life and אין בו דעה
ein bo de'ah means does not use. I think that's clear from
this statement as well. מתקיף לה רב אחא קרחינא. Maskif lah Rav
Achah Karchinah. So רב אחא קרחינא Rav Achah Karchinah asked on this.
אלא מעתה גדולה נקמה שנתנה בין שתי אותיות. Ella me'atah, gedolah nekamah
shenitnah bein shtei osiyos. So
how about you say, oh, great is intellect, great is the מקדש,
Mikdash, how about vengeance? That's also between two names of God. Where
do you get it? שנאמר אל נקמות השם. shene'emar El nekamot Hashem.
God of vengeance is God. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
said back to him: אין, In, yes! למילתה גדולה היא, lemilsayehi gedolah
hi, when it's appropriate, that is a great thing. Not you should
always go around being vengeful, but there are times you have to
act that way and then it's important to act that way. והאי
דאמר עולא, Veha'i de'amar Ulla, that's what עולא Ulla says. שתי נקמות
הללו למה, Shtei nekamot hallalu lamah,
why does it say נקמות nekamot twice? אל נקמות השם אל נקמות
הופיע, El nekamot Hashem El nekamot hofia, say נקמה nekamah twice? אחת
לטובה ואחת
לרעה, achas letovah ve'achas lera'ah,
one for good, one for evil. Meaning one to benefit those that
have done good and the other to punish those who have done
evil. לטובה דכתיב הופיע מהר פארן, letovah dechtiv hofia mehar Paran,
and God revealed himself from מהר פארן. mehar Paran. Not exactly clear
why or how that's לטובה, letovah, I'll explain in a minute. לרעה
דכתיב אל נקמות השם אל נקמות הופיע, lera'ah dechtiv El nekamot Hashem
El nekamot hofia,
God of vengeance is God. So where הופיע מהר פארן, hofia mehar
Paran, what does it have to do with vengeance and where is
that לטובה? letovah? So Rashi says, and it seems to be the
intent of the גמרא, Gemara, that it's referring to a מדרש Midrash
that says that when the other nations did not accept the תורה,
Torah, therefore God went and gave the תורה Torah to ישראל. Israel.
Actually, it goes even further to say that therefore God made sort
of whatever, it raises other גמרות Gemaros that raises other concerns and
issues. But anyway, somehow that the vengeance of the other nations that
ישראל Yisrael were the beneficiaries of it. So this is interesting because
I want to say two things about this and then we'll move
on in addition to this little discussion about what it mean יש
yesh and אין בו דעה. ein bo de'ah. Number one is it's
the same רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that said before if you remember
that we spent a minute ago that said תפילה Tefilah is greater
than קרבנות. Korbanot. And he also said when there's no בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash then it's from the time of the חורבן הבית Churban
habayis that it's like the gates of prayer have been sealed. So
the same רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that had those almost like statements
about תפילה Tefilah was without קרבנות, Korbanot, but if we don't have
a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash here saying that if you live a
life of דעה de'ah then it's כאילו נבנה מקדש בימיו. ke'ilu nivneh
Mikdash beyamav. So in a way it's a question about how do
we continue to live a life of religious meaning without a בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and it's quite interesting if you put those various
statements together. Well תפילה Tefilah still matters, what about the fact that
it's like ננעלו שערי תפילה? nin'alu sha'arei Tefilah? Okay, but if you're
living a life of דעה de'ah then it's כאילו נבנה מקדש בימיו
ke'ilu nivneh Mikdash beyamav and then God you are in a profound
and intimate relationship with God. So I think it's nice to put
those points together. The other thing that I will say is about
this אל נקמות השם. El nekamot Hashem. Is this whole interesting question
because there's a מצווה mitzvah of והלכת בדרכיו, vehalachta bidrachav, going in
God's
ways. So and normally in one way in which that's interpreted by
חז"ל Chazal is מה הוא רחום אף אתה רחום מה הוא חנון
אף אתה חנון. mah hu rachum af atah rachum mah hu chanun
af atah chanun. He is compassionate, He has lovingkindness, you should be
compassionate. Well the question of course is
why are you only focusing on those attributes of God? What about
the fact that when God gets angry he wipes out 3,000
people? Maybe that should be והלכת בדרכיו. vehalachta bidrachav. So רמב"ם Rambam
has an answer to this and רמב"ם Rambam says the reason we
should focus on the names that are given to God. מה הוא
רחום, mah hu rachum, God is called רחום, rachum, it's as if
he's called חנון chanun and so on and those names are telling
us which are sort of the attributes that are the divine attributes
that should be emulated. So I mentioned this in the context here
of אל נקמות השם, El nekamot Hashem, and is נקמה nekamah an
aspect of God that we should be emulating? Is that a positive
thing or not? So the גמרא Gemara says well maybe in its
right context. But who's to define what's its right context and what
are the limits of that? So it does raise interesting general those
broader questions about these aspects and attributes of God and which ones
are being held up for emulation.
Yes, back to the one on knowledge that that פסוק pasuk there
is actually from חנה's Chanah prayer and the context implies that she
might have been referring to עלי. Eli.
עלי Eli meaning עלי?
Eli? עלי, Eli, yes, for אל דעות השם, El de'ot Hashem, but
then immediately before she's complaining about arrogance and pride
and her enemies, and so the context I would interpret is referring
to the fact that people didn't understand that she wasn't drunk and
עלי Eli should have known better.
Oh, okay, maybe.
So this is why I would—interesting, not of
people
in general.
I would say the opposite. The sentence says you're not permitted to
have compassion, it means ordinarily people that you would naturally have compassion
for, don't have compassion for them.
Yeah, I hear, I just don't think so, and I think that
the next פסוק Pasuk about the next statement about יש בו דעה
yesh bo de'ah does not mean just has it but means uses
it. So anyway, okay, we've dealt, we've already, I think everybody has
said what they need to say about that. Let's move on. הגמרא
HaGemara says like this: four lines down of the wide lines: ובהיא
אומר אמר רבי עקיבא רביעית. v'behavi omer amar Rabbi Akiva revi'it. So
now Rabbi Akiva says you say חונן הדעת Chonen HaDa'at as its
own independent
ברכה. bracha. אמר רב שמן בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rav
Shemen bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look.
אנשי כנסת הגדולה תיקנו להם לישראל ברכות ותפילות קדושות והבדלות. Anshei Knesset
HaGedolah tiknu lahem l'Yisrael brachot u'tfilot kdushot v'havdalot. Interesting. Okay, so the
אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset HaGedolah have established for Israel, like this
is a general assumption in the גמרא Gemara that the תפילות tfilot
were written by אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Anshei Knesset HaGedolah which by the
way is before the חורבן הבית churban habayit getting back to this
idea that תפילות tfilot are not just a substitute for קרבנות, korbanot,
it was during the beginning of the בית שני Bayit Sheni period
of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. They established the
ברכות, brachos, the תפילות, tfilot, which is presumably the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh
Esrei, קדושה, kdushah, הבדלה. havdalah. So נחזי היכא תיקון? nachzei heicha tikun?
How could there be this debate about whether there's a separate ברכה
bracha of חונן הדעת? Chonen HaDa'at? Let's just find out what the
original תקנה takkanah was. We had a similar question in the גמרא
Gemara before about תקנת עזרא takkanat Ezra about a בעל קרי. ba'al
keri. Let's just figure out what the תקנה takkanah was. And as
תוספות Tosafot says, I mean we've been דאווענינג davening since then, so
if we've been דאווענינג davening since then how could there be a
debate, which is, you know, always the question? How is there a
debate about things which are widespread, about what the facts are? Like
how is there a debate of רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם, Rabbeinu
Tam, the order of the פרשיות parshiyot that they appear in תפילין?
tefillin? Let's just look around and see what people are doing. So,
you know, the most obvious answer to that is, well, maybe there's
a variation in practice and there's a debate about which is the
correct one. And actually in the בר כוכבא Bar Kochba caves they
found תפילין tefillin that both, that have both orders of the תפילין,
tefillin, both רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. So you know
it shows you that sometimes, yeah, there is. Sometimes somebody will get
up and say what everybody is doing is wrong, I'm going to
go back to the way it should be. But you know, but
sometimes, so that's the first question. What have we been דאווענינג davening
until now? Every מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbat we say חונן הדעת. Chonen
HaDa'at. I don't understand. What have we been doing it for, you
know, let's just see. So presumably there's actually a variation in practice,
but the גמרא Gemara is saying, well, you know, and it's clear,
you know, that the תפילות tfilot did not really coalesce even when
the גמרא Gemara speaks about eighteen ברכות. brachos. There was certain latitude;
תוספתא Tosefta talks about if you want to combine these ברכות brachos
or you want to say it this way. There was a whole
period, even when they had a basic form, that there was a
certain divergence of practice. But the גמרא Gemara is saying, okay, but
let's figure out, I mean, shouldn't it have been clear what the
תקנה takkanah was, what we've been doing since then fine? So the
גמרא Gemara says, let's take a look. אמר ליה, Amar lei, בתחילה
קבעוה בתפילה. betichilah kvauha bitfilah. No,
here's the way הבדלה havdalah went through a process. First it was
included in the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. העשירו, He'ashiru, then people, the
community society got a little wealthier, and they were able to give
it more of an important sort of ritual, קבעוה על הכוס, kvauha
al hakos, and they make הבדלה על הכוס. havdalah al hakos. So
presumably they took it out of שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. They want
to do הבדלה מוצאי שבת, havdalah Motzaei Shabbat, now they're able to
demand that people do it on a כוס, kos, on a cup
of wine. We're going to make that into the ritual and we
took it out of
שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Then הענו, He'anu, they became poor
again, חזרו וקבעוה בתפילה. chazru u'kvauha bitfilah. So let's go back to
the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So since there was a, there was
an interruption in the practice, there was a period they were only
doing it על הכוס al hakos and not in שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh
Esrei, then there was a, then they forgot how it used to
be. Was it incorporated in חונן הדעת? Chonen HaDa'at? Was it a
separate ברכה? bracha? And that's how we lost track of what it
used to be. Don't change the what, don't change things. That's the
message. והם אמרו, המבדיל בתפילה צריך שיבדיל על הכוס. V'heim amru hamavdil
bitfilah tzarich sheyavdil al hakos. And then they also said even now
like once they said that they, once they put it back in
the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, they said, you know what, now even
though you're saying it in שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, okay if you
just say in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei you're יוצא yotzei הבדלה, havdalah,
but you still should do it again על הכוס. al hakos. Actually
על הכוס al hakos has another aspect to the הבדלה havdalah which
is not just making הבדלה havdalah but allowing you then to eat
on מוצאי שבת. Motzaei Shabbat. So they now, then now we have
it that we have it both parts of the תקנה. takkanah. איתמר
נמי, Itmar nami, it was also taught, אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, אנשי
כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset HaGedolah, תיקנו להם לישראל ברכות ותפילות קדושות והבדלות.
tiknu lahem l'Yisrael brachot u'tfilot kdushot v'havdalot. So we've got a ברייתא,
braita, all of this liturgy if you would was established by אנשי
כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Knesset HaGedolah. בתחילה קבעוה בתפילה, Betichilah kvauha bitfilah, והבדלות,
v'havdalot, excuse me, there's a comma, והבדלות. v'havdalot. When it comes to
הבדלה, havdalah, בתחילה קבעוה בתפילה, betichilah kvauha bitfilah, העשירו קבעוה על הכוס,
he'ashiru kvauha al hakos, חזרו והענו קבעוה בתפילה. chazru v'he'anu kvauha bitfilah.
So they went back and forth between הבדלה, havdalah, between שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei and על הכוס. al hakos. והם אמרו V'heim amru, המבדיל
בתפילה צריך שיבדיל על הכוס. hamavdil bitfilah tzarich sheyavdil al hakos. And
then they said, you know what, now we're putting it back in
the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and you should also still do it
on כוס. kos. Of course the question is that if they're poor
and they had to take it away from the כוס kos and
put it back onto the הבדלה, havdalah, how are they also saying
now you have to do both in, and put back in שמונה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, both in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and על הכוס?
al hakos? So maybe it meant like even if you can't afford
the כוס kos you
were יוצא yotzei through the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. איתמר נמי, Itmar
nami, it's been
said also, איתמר נמי itmar nami that we didn't have רבי... Rabbi...
No except that this was just a... This was just a quote
of a ברייתא braita of others said the same thing, others saying
the same thing. Okay. איתמר נמי, itmar namei, אמר רבא ורב יוסף
דאמרי תרווייהו amar Rava veRav Yosef d'amri tarvaihu המבדיל בתפילה צריך שיבדיל
על הכוס. hamavdil bitfillah tzarich sheyavdil al haccos.
Now we're moving on between the question about we lost track of
where the הבדלה havdalah was, was it a separate ברכה, bracha, to
this הלכה halacha that it is both in the שמנה עשרה Shmoneh
Esreh and על הכוס, al haccos, and even if you do שמנה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, you should still be doing it על הכוס. al
haccos. אמר רבא, amar Rava, ומותבינן אשמעתין, umotivinan ashmattin, and so we
ask on our teaching, on our סוגיא: sugya: טעה ולא הזכיר גבורות
גשמים בתחיית המתים, ta'ah velo hizkir gevurot geshamim bitchiyat hametim,
and we have a ברייתא braita we quoted this before, that if
somebody forgot to mention משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם, mashiv haruach umorid hagashem,
ושאלה בברכת
השנים, ushe'elah bebirchat hashanim, or forgot to say ותן טל ומטר לברכה
veten tal umatar livracha in the right place, מחזירין אותו, machzirin oto,
you make them go back to the right place. Another גמרא Gemara
said that if you haven't yet finished שומע תפילה, shome'a tefillah, you
can add משיב הרוח mashiv haruach there. But okay, you go back.
ותן
טל ומטר,
veten tal
umatar, right, not משיב הרוח. mashiv haruach.
I'm sorry, did I say that? I misspoke, I misspoke then. Okay,
right. If you miss משיב הרוח mashiv haruach then you can't, you
can't put it in שומע תפילה shome'a tefillah because שומע תפילה shome'a
tefillah is about בקשה. bakasha. If you miss ותן טל ומטר, veten
tal umatar, you put in שומע תפילה. shome'a tefillah. But anyway, if
you miss even the שומע תפילה, shome'a tefillah, all these things are
things you need to go back for if you can't put them
elsewhere. והבדלה בחונן הדעת, vehavdalah bechonen hada'at, you say הבדלה havdalah in
חונן הדעת, chonen hada'at, אין מחזירין אותו, ein machzirin oto, but if
you missed הבדלה havdalah in חונן הדעת, chonen hada'at, you do not
make the person go back. Why? מפני שיכול לאומרה על הכוס, mipnei
sheyachol leomra al haccos,
because you can say it on a cup of wine. As I
mentioned the other day also, even if you haven't yet finished שומע
תפילה, shome'a tefillah, there's some debate but generally the overwhelming consensus is
you do not say הבדלה havdalah in שומע תפילה shome'a tefillah because
it's not a בקשה. bakasha. It's more about just describing that God
is המבדיל בין קודש לחול. hamavdil bein kodesh lechol. So you don't
do it in שומע תפילה. shome'a tefillah. So if you missed in
חונן הדעת, chonen hada'at, fine, you missed it, but you'll say it
on the כוס של יין cos shel yayin so you don't have
to worry about that. Now, so the גמרא, Gemara, so anyway, so
now why is that a question? Because the way this says it
is if you missed it in שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, don't worry,
you have an option to make it up, you can make it
always על הכוס. al haccos. But it sounds like you're making it
על הכוס al haccos when you forgot to say it in שמנה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, but you wouldn't regularly do it על הכוס. al
haccos. That's the question. It says מפני שיכול לאומרה על הכוס, mipnei
sheyachol leomra al haccos, because you have the option of doing it
על הכוס. al haccos. So how can you say we always have
to do it? So the גמרא Gemara says לא תימא מפני שיכול
לאומרה על הכוס, lo teima mipnei sheyachol leomra al haccos, you have
the option of doing it, אלא אימא מפני שאומרה על הכוס, ela
eima mipnei sheomra al haccos, you're anyway going to do it על
הכוס. al haccos. So if you missed it in שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh
Esreh, don't worry, you're anyway going to do it על הכוס al
haccos and we have both components present. One minute. איתמר נמי, itmar
namei, was also taught, אמר רבי בנימין בר יפת, amar Rabbi Binyamin
bar Yefet, שאל רבי יוסי את רבי יוחנן בצידן, sha'al Rabbi Yosi
et Rabbi Yochanan beTzidan, Rabbi Yosi asked Rabbi Yochanan in Sidon, ואמרי
לה רבי שמעון בן יעקב דמן צור, veamrei lah Rabbi Shimon ben
Yaakov demin Tzur, and some say Rabbi Shimon ben Yaakov from Tyre—interesting
here we have specific geographic placements—את רבי יוחנן, et Rabbi Yochanan, asked
Rabbi Yochanan, ואנא שמעית, va'ana sham'it, and I heard it, I heard
them directly. Here was the question: המבדיל בתפילה צריך שיבדיל על הכוס
או לא? hamavdil bitfillah tzarich sheyavdil al haccos o lo? If somebody
makes הבדלה havdalah in שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, do they have to
do it here also? You would imagine like, what question is that?
What's everybody doing every מוצאי שבת, motzei Shabbat, right? Hopefully people are
doing הבדלה havdalah in תפילה tefillah and they make it על הכוס
al haccos or not. So again it wonders sort of what was
the practice. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar leih, צריך שיבדיל על הכוס, tzarich
sheyavdil al haccos, you have to. Now I should say by the
way, to some degree you could just say, okay, this is a
vestige of having moved back and forth and we want to retain
the idea that it's more ritualized when it's על הכוס, al haccos,
but we don't want to sort of lose the idea that, you
know, it just is part of שמנה עשרה. Shmoneh Esreh. But it
also should be noted that the הבדלה על הכוס, havdalah al haccos,
as I mentioned very quickly before, serves another purpose as well in
addition to the ritualized, because obviously it's a counterpart to the קידוש
על הכוס. Kiddush al haccos. And the same way the קידוש על
הכוס Kiddush al haccos is like במקום סעודה, bemakom seudah, we don't
demand that הבדלה על הכוס havdalah al haccos be במקום סעודה, bemakom
seudah, but it serves a similar function as like framing it as
sort of, you know, סעודת שבת seudat Shabbat is what הבדלה havdalah
does, and הבדלה על הכוס havdalah al haccos sort of frames the
eating now as like the weekday eating and not the Shabbat eating
because that's the על הכוס, al haccos, it starts, connects to the
wine and to something that's being consumed. And that's why the הלכה
halacha is that even if you say הבדלה havdalah in שמנה עשרה,
Shmoneh Esreh, you're not allowed to eat מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbat until
you do הבדלה על הכוס. havdalah al haccos. So it does actually
serve, it's not just redundant and oh we also get this other
ritual of על היין, al hayayin, actually it winds up serving an
additional function that's not served by the הבדלה havdalah in שמנה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esreh.
I like the idea that you can say הבדלה havdalah until Tuesday.
Right, so that also if you miss it על הכוס al haccos
you have time that you can say it.
But you can't eat, right? I mean...
yeah, but you're not supposed to until you make הבדלה, havdalah, right?
Oh, so if you forgot, presumably you have the eating, but yeah.
So I say the הבדלה havdalah section in the שמנה עשרה. Shmoneh
Esreh. Right. At what point have I officially ended שבת Shabbat or
can do מלאכה? melacha? Is it at the end of the הבדלה
havdalah section, the end of the fourth ברכה, bracha, or the end
of the entire שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, or the end of the
entire תפילה? tefillah?
Basically I'd say as soon as you say the הבדלה havdalah section,
although I don't know what מלאכה melacha you're doing in the middle
of your שמנה עשרה?
Shmoneh Esreh? Oh, in case I have to go to the bathroom
and I need to turn the light on.
In the middle of your שמנה עשרה? Shmoneh Esreh? Yeah. Anyway, but
as soon as you say המבדיל בין קודש לחול. hamavdil bein kodesh
lechol. Somebody who's in a position where they can't דאוון, davven, where
they can't
דאוון. davven. Let's say you went out of order, right? You made
הבדלה על הכוס Havdalah al hakos and you haven't yet דאוונד שמנה
עשרה. davened Shemoneh Esrei. So since על הכוס al hakos gets both,
right? It's הבדלה Havdalah and it's על הכוס, al hakos, maybe you
shouldn't have to do it in שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק קל וחומר מתפילה. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
kal vachomer mitfillah. I'll make a קל וחומר kal vachomer from דאווננינג.
davening. מה תפילה דעיקר תקנתא היא, Mah tfillah d'ikar takanta hi, so
we stayed... so if I said הבדלה על הכוס Havdalah al hakos
was better, you have the ritual of על הכוס, al hakos, but
the Gemara says the opposite. תפילה Tfillah is where it was fundamentally,
originally put in שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. אמי המבדיל בתפילה טורח שיבדיל
על הכוס, Ami hamavdil bitfillah torech sheyavdil al hakos, even when you
do the proper with the original place of תפילה, tfillah, we still
want you to do the other form of doing it on על
הכוס. al hakos. המבדיל על הכוס דלאו עיקר תקנתא היא, Hamavdil al
hakos d'lav ikar takanta hi, so when you do על הכוס al
hakos although you get the ritual of the wine that wasn't where
it primarily was established, לא כל שכן, lo kol shekein, how much
more so should we want to insist that you also get it
in its primary location in שמנה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? תני רב אחא
ריכא קמיה דרב חיננא. Tanya Rav Acha Rikha kammai d'Rav Chinana. So
רב אחא ריכא Rav Acha Rikha taught in front of רב חיננא,
Rav Chinana, המבדיל בתפילה משובח יותר ממי שיבדיל על הכוס. hamavdil bitfillah
meshubach yoter mimi sheyavdil al hakos.
If you say it in שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, that's better than
על הכוס, al hakos, which was implicit in what we said before.
Again, it's quite funny then why when they got rich did they
switch it to the כוס? kos? Just keep it in the שמנה
עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Anyway, ואם הבדיל בזו ובזו
ינוחו לו ברכות על ראשו, ve'im hivdil b'zu u'v'zu yanuchu lo brachot
al rosho,
blessings should be come on your head, meaning how wonderful it is
that you've done both. So the problem is that that makes it
sound like a normal person has an option which one to do.
Should you want to do both? Oh, it's beautiful. But really you
could pick which one and it's better to do it in שמנה
עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's got a problem with that.
הגופא קשיא, Hagufa kashya, one minute, this is a problem. אמרת המבדיל
בתפילה משובח יותר ממי שיבדיל על הכוס, Amart hamavdil bitfillah meshubach yoter
mimi sheyavdil al hakos, if you do it in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh
Esrei it's better than doing it on a cup of wine. אמר
תפילה לחודה סגי, Amar tfillah l'chudah sagi, so you see that it's
sufficient to do it in שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. הדר תניא, Hadar
tanya, then you say ואם הבדיל בזו ובזו ינוחו לו ברכות על
ראשו, ve'im hivdil b'zu u'v'zu yanuchu lo brachot al rosho, if you
do it in both blessings should descend on your head. וכיון דנפיק
ליה בחדא, Vekivan d'nafik leh b'chada, once you're already יוצא yotze with
שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, איפטר, iftar, then you're exempt. והויא ברכה שאינה
צריכה, Vehavya brachah she'eina tzrichah, then it's a non-necessary ברכה. brachah. ואמר
רב ואיתימא ריש לקיש ואמרי לה רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש ואמרי תרווייהו
כל מברך ברכה שאינה צריכה, Ve'amar Rav va'itayma Reish Lakish, v'amri leh
Rabbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish, v'amri taveihu, kol mevarech brachah she'eina tzrichah, if
you make a ברכה brachah that's not necessary, עובר משום לא תשא,
over mishum lo tisa, that you transgress not taking God's name in
vain. By the way, generally that's assumed to be an אסמכתא, asmachtah,
although I should mention that ספרדים Sephardim are much more concerned about
issues of ברכה שאינה צריכה brachah she'eina tzrichah and ברכה לבטלה brachah
levatalah because a number of ספרדי פוסקים Sephardic poskim assume that it's
a real transgression of לא תשא, lo tisa, of a biblical לא
תשא. lo tisa. Normally we assume that that's only that that's meant
as an אסמכתא. asmachtah. Anyway, so when did we have this idea
that, you know, you can have an option of making another ברכה?
brachah? If this is הבדלה, Havdalah, it's הבדלה, Havdalah, then you shouldn't
be able to do it twice. And by the way, parenthetically, you
should say it's against what we've said until now. Until now we've
said you have the obligation to say it in both. Here we
see an approach that you have the option of doing one or
the other. So it does really seem that there were these two
camps, that for a while there was a sense of you have
the option and then it coalesced to be a position no you
have to do both. But where... but the גמרא Gemara wants to
sort of take this position of option and challenges it by how
then how could it have been even possible to do both? And
says, אלא אימא ella eima fine read it like we've... reread it
הכי אם הבדילו בזו ובזו ולא הבדיל בזו ינוחו לו ברכות על
ראשו. hachi: im hivdilu b'zu u'v'zu v'lo hivdil b'zu, yanuchu lo brachot
al rosho. So actually it says it deals with the ברכה שאינה
צריכה brachah she'eina tzrichah problem, but it really has it as a
different position than we've been saying now. It's better to do it
in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei than על הכוס, al hakos, but if
you do both, then you've got... but... and if you do only
one, then you're blessed. If you do both you're doing something wrong
because it's a ברכה שאינה צריכה. brachah she'eina tzrichah. So now the
גמרא Gemara has basically made... established, you know, that there's actually a
debate about this. Are you supposed to do both or supposed to
do one and you should choose which one. One minute, so בעי
מיניה רב חסדא מרב ששת, ba'ei minei Rav Chisda me'Rav Sheshet, טעה
בזו ובזו מהו? ta b'zu u'v'zu mahu? So let's say you forgot
to say it in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and you forgot to
do it that night. So you didn't do it על הכוס, al
hakos, now what does it mean טעה? ta? So do it על
הכוס? al hakos? But maybe it means you already drank wine. It's
an interesting question, is there a point after which you can't do
it על הכוס al hakos anymore? So what exactly is the scenario
of טעה בזו ובזו? ta b'zu u'v'zu? But somehow you've missed both
opportunities. So what should you do now? Do you go back and
do שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei again? So אמר ליה, amar leh, he
said to him, טעה בזו ובזו חוזר לראש. ta b'zu u'v'zu chozer
l'rosh. Ah, if you missed both then you have to do שמנה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei again. This is fascinating. What does it mean to
miss הבדלה על הכוס? Havdalah al hakos? Right? Does it mean you
ate? Does it mean you drank wine? Does it mean it's the
next morning? Next morning what are you doing going back to מעריב?
Maariv? Anyway, somehow there's an idea of missing הבדלה על היין. Havdalah
al hayayin. אמר ליה רבינא לרבא, Amar leh Ravina l'Rava, sorry, Ravina
said to רבא, Rava, הלכתא מאי? hilchata mai? That was very... that's
very nice, but do we really פסקן pasken that way? What's the
הלכה? halachah? אמר ליה כי קידוש, Amar leh ki Kiddush, it's like
קידוש. Kiddush. מה קידוש אף על גב דמקדש בתפילה מקדש אכסא, Mah
Kiddush af al gav d'mekadesh bitfillah mekadesh akasa, so this is going
back by the way to not this question of if you missed
both but to the earlier issue about do you say it in
one or the other or do you say it in both? And
he says it's just like קידוש, Kiddush, again this very parallel of
הבדלה Havdalah to קידוש. Kiddush. By קידוש, Kiddush, even though you say
in שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, you say... מקדש השבת Mekadesh Hashabbat you're
going to say a קידוש על הכוס Kiddush Al Hakos Friday night.
מקדש אכסא Mekadesh Akasa you do it again on the cup of
wine. אף על גב דנמי Af al gav de-nami even by הבדלה
Havdalah אף על גב דאבדלתא בצלותא af al gav de-avdelta bitslusa even
though you do it in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei המבדיל Hamavdil המבדיל
על הכוס Hamavdil Al Hakos there's an additional ritual of doing it
על הכוס al hakos and as I said maybe particularly framed around
the eating. It is interesting by the way though that the גמרא
Gemara does not go back and say the whole issue about this
discussion about טעה בזו ובזו ta'ah be-zu u-ve-zu and what exactly is
the scenario about that but there's a way in which at least
according to the גמרא Gemara you could be חוזר לראש. chozer lerosh.
Yes.
This seems to be going according only to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
who says that this is a special that there's a separate ברכה
bracha because there's a difference between הבדלה Havdalah in חונן הדעת Chonen
Hada'as and מקדש השבת. Mekadesh Hashabbat.
That is true but that's because on שבת Shabbat you have only
you're right one it's ממש הברכה mamash habracha of מקדש השבת Mekadesh
Hashabbat but then it's even more קל וחומר kal vachomer if you
make an explicit ברכה bracha מקדש השבת Mekadesh Hashabbat and you're still
going to do a קידוש Kiddush then how much more so הבדלה
Havdalah which wasn't even a special ברכה bracha it was just inserted
that even though you do it in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei you
still need to do it על הכוס. al hakos. If anything it's
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Yes.
Well there's another issue which is somewhat related. You do הבדלה Havdalah
in שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei then you do הבדלה Havdalah in שול
shul over כוס kos and then you go home and make הבדלה
Havdalah at home with your family when you've already fulfilled your obligation.
Right. That's a separate issue about אף על פי שיצא מוציא af
al pi she-yatza motzi and not our issue right now. Okay so
let's keep on going. We have רבי אליעזר אומר בהודאה. Rabbi Eliezer
omer behoda'ah. So the גמרא Gemara you say it in מודים. Modim.
רב זירא הוי רכיב חמרא Rav Zeira hava rachiv chamra הוי קא
שגי ואזיל. hava ka shagi ve-azil. רב זירא Rav Zeira was riding
on a donkey he was riding along והוי קא שגי ואזיל רבי
חייא בר אבין בתריה. ve-hava ka shagi ve-azil Rabbi Chiya bar Avin
basreih. And רבי חייא בר אבין Rabbi Chiya bar Avin was riding
along with him after him. אמר ליה. Amar leih. So he said
so רבי חייא בר אבין Rabbi Chiya bar Avin said to רב
זירא Rav Zeira ודאי דאמרת משמיה דרבי יוחנן vadai de-amart mishmei de-Rabbi
Yochanan you certainly must I know that you've said in the name
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan הלכה כרבי אליעזר ביום טוב שחל להיות
אחר שבת Halacha ke-Rabbi Eliezer beyom tov she-chal lihyos achar Shabbat is
it true that you've said or I was is it true that
you've said in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that we
rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer when יום טוב Yom Tov happens
after שבת. Shabbat. When יום טוב Yom Tov happens after שבת Shabbat
you have to say הבדלה Havdalah you can't say it in חונן
הדעת Chonen Hada'as there is no חונן הדעת. Chonen Hada'as. Where do
you say הבדלה? Havdalah? So we have to now maybe choose between
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer maybe even you
say it in a ברכה בפני עצמה bracha bifnei atzmah or maybe
you say it in מודים. Modim. So he says maybe is this
true what you say that we rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and we say it in
מודים? Modim? אמר ליה אין. Amar leih in. אין In excuse me
excuse me אין in excuse me I'm jumping ahead. The גמרא Gemara
is going to rules in אין in yes. So we do like
that we say like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan so we say like
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So the גמרא Gemara asks הלכה מכלל דפליגי?
Halacha miklal de-pligi? So if it's הלכה halacha it implies that there's
a debate about it maybe everybody agrees since there is no option
to say it in חונן הדעת. Chonen Hada'as. So the גמרא Gemara
says ולא פליגי? Velo pligi? How could you think that they don't
disagree? והא פליגי רבנן. Veha pligi rabanan. The רבנן Rabanan argue. So
the גמרא Gemara says no one minute אימא דפליגי רבנן eima de-pligi
rabanan when did they argue? בשאר ימות השנה. Beshear yemot hashana. In
the rest of the year
ביום טוב שחל להיות אחר שבת beyom tov she-chal lihyos achar Shabbat
מי פליגי? mi pligi?
Who says they argue? Maybe if you can't say it in חונן
הדעת Chonen Hada'as maybe they agree you say it in מודים. Modim.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute והא פליג רבי עקיבא. veha
pelig Rabbi Akiva. We know that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would hold
his position even יום טוב Yom Tov after שבת Shabbat as a
separate ברכה bracha so maybe so maybe even though the רבנן Rabanan
don't disagree we still have רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and therefore maybe
we should rule like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and say it as
a separate ברכה. bracha. So the גמרא Gemara answers back one minute
אטו כל השנה כולה מי עבדינן כרבי עקיבא דהשתא הכא נעביד כוותיה?
atu kol hashana kula mi avdinan ke-Rabbi Akiva de-hashta hacha na'avid kevaseih?
The rest of the year we don't act like רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva now here you want us to act like רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and even though you don't now have the option of saying
it in חונן הדעת Chonen Hada'as nevertheless כל השנה כולה מאי טעמא
לא עבדינן כרבי עקיבא? kol hashana kula mai ta'ama lo avdinan ke-Rabbi
Akiva? Why do we not normally act like him? דתמני סרי תיקון
תשע סרי לא תיקון. de-tamnei sari tikkun taysha sari lo tikkun. That
18 were enacted 19 were not enacted. הכא נמי. Hacha nami. So
here too יום טוב Yom Tov after שבת Shabbat don't tell me
oh even though the רבנן Rabanan might not argue we should run
in maybe we should do רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? No the same
logic would apply to not do רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. שבע תיקון
תמני לא תיקון. sheva tikkun tamnei lo tikkun. There are seven enacted
and not eight. There are seven ברכות brachos for יום טוב Yom
Tov and not eight. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva we generally reject
we don't add ברכות. brachos. The רבנן Rabanan say put it in
חונן הדעת. Chonen Hada'as. We don't have that option so presumably מוצאי
שבת Motzei Shabbat which is יום טוב Yom Tov we should put
it in מודים Modim like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and maybe even
the רבנן Rabanan agree with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer if there's no
other option. So that's what's being said right now. So now the
גמרא Gemara says let's see what the conclusion is of this. So
the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה לאו הלכה איתמר אלא מטין איתמר. amar leih lav halacha
itmar ela matin itmar. So the
it wasn't the הלכה halacha that was said but it was stated
we're inclined to say like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer afterwards which means
like yeah if you ask me for a פסק psak that's what
I'll tell you but I'm not going to go ahead and say
this is make a big announcement this is how we פסקן. pasken.
We're inclined to say like that. דאיתמר רבי יצחק בר אבדימי אמר
משום רבינו. de-itmar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi amar mishum Rabbeinu. רבי יצחק
בר אבדימי Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi says in the name of רבינו
Rabbeinu which רש"י Rashi says I think is who רב. Rav.
אה מה רש"י אומר? ah ma Rashi omer? It's רבינו. Rabbeinu.
רב Rav yes thank you. הלכה. Halacha. So we rule like רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer we say it in מודים. Modim. say it in
מודים modim *Modim* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* מוצאי שבת *Motza'ei Shabbos* which
is יום טוב *Yom Tov*. ואמרי לה *ve'amri lei*, some say מטה
*mattei*. We incline towards that position. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* אמר amar,
*amar* מודים *Modim*, that not that... everybody agrees, meaning as the גמרא'ס
*Gemara's* question before was, is it even debated by יום טוב *Yom
Tov* which is מוצאי שבת *Motza'ei Shabbos* because where else are you
going to say it? So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says we don't
have to say הלכה *halakha*, actually מודים *Modim*, everybody agrees that that's
we say that, you know, there's no debate מוצאי שבת *Motza'ei Shabbos*
when it's יום טוב *Yom Tov*. רבי חייא בר אבא *Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba* אמר *amar* נראין *nirin*. It appears that רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* is correct in this case, that you'd say it in מודים
*Modim*, but that's less even less of an endorsement than מטה *mattei*.
אמר רב זירא *Amar Rav Zeira*, נקוט דרבי חייא בר אבא בידך
*nekot deRabbi Chiya bar Abba beyadecha*. Take רבי חייא בר אבא'ס *Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba's* position that he just said that it's like נראין
*nirin*, you know, which is like okay, a little bit it seems
like it's correct which is the most tepid endorsement. Why? דדייק וגמר
שמעתתא מפומא
דמרה שפיר *dedayyek vegamar shmaitata mipuma demarei shapir* כרחבה דפומבדיתא *keRechava dePumbedita*.
Because he was very careful to make sure that he got the
exact language that his רבי *Rebbi* used as careful as רחבה דפומבדיתא
*Rechava dePumbedita*. How was רחבה דפומבדיתא *Rechava dePumbedita* so careful? דאמר רחבה
אמר רב יהודה *de'amar Rechava amar Rav Yehuda*, הר הבית סטיו כפול
היה *Har HaBayis stav kaful haya*. The Temple Mount had like a
double סטיו *stav*, which was... והאי סטיו לפנים מסטיו *veha'ei stav lifnim
mistav* and it was a סטיו *stav*, a step, what there's a
Greek word for this, a stail, a colonnade, but I think it's
something that sounds like סטיו *stav*, what, סטוא *stoa*? סטוא *stoa*, thank
you. A סטוא *stoa* inside of a סטוא *stoa*. So how does
that prove he was very careful with the language? Because the normal
rabbinic term for this is אצטבא *istaba*. So he said סטיו *stav*
so you see he very was careful to use the same language
his רבי *Rebbi* used. And here too, these all of these versions
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands might have just been a corruption or
are very you know, people didn't hear correctly. מודים *Modim*, מטה *mattei*,
נראין *nirin*, you know, maybe they're you know, so so what really
was said? Which way? So says you should go like רבי חייא
בר אבא *Rabbi Chiya bar Abba* who actually just said נראין *nirin*,
which was the weakest but because he's very careful to get exactly
the language that was used. Okay, so now where we are is
it sounds like we would say that since we don't really have
another option, whether you said מודים *Modim* or מטה *mattei* or נראין
*nirin*, it sounds like we would say הבדלה *havdala* in מודים *Modim*,
another מודים *Modim*, you know, in הודאה *hoda'ah* on when it's יום
טוב *Yom Tov* is מוצאי שבת *Motza'ei Shabbos*. We know we don't
do that. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concludes. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concludes like this. So אמר רב יוסף *amar
Rav Yosef*, אנא לא האיי דענא ולא האיי דענא *ana lo ha'ei
da'ana velo ha'ei da'ana*. I don't know this one, I don't know
that one. I don't know about מודים *Modim*, נראין *nirin*, מטה *mattei*,
I don't know about any of that. אלא מדרב ושמואל דענא *Ella
midRav uShmuel da'ana*. I know what רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* says.
דתקינו לן מרגניתא בבבל *detakinu lan marganisa beVavel*. This is a very
nice language. They established for us this pearl in בבל *Bavel*. They
came up with a beautiful language for the liturgy. It's a pearl.
What is this pearl? ותודיענו *Vatodieinu* ה' אלוהינו *Hashem Elokeinu* את משפטי
צדקך *es mishpetei tzidkecha* ותלמדנו לעשות חוקי רצונך *vatsalmedinu la'asos chukei retzonecha*
ותנחילנו זמני ששון וחגי נדבה *vatsanchileinu zamanei sason vechagei nedava* ותורישנו קדושת
שבת וכבוד מועד וחגיגת הרגל *vesorisheinu kedushas Shabbos uchevod mo'ed vechagigas haregel*.
בין קדושת שבת לקדושת יום טוב הבדלת *Bein kedushas Shabbos likedushas Yom
Tov hivdalta* ואת יום השביעי מששת ימי המעשה קידשת *ve'es yom hashevi'i
misheshes yemei hama'aseh kidashta*. הבדלת וקידשת את עמך ישראל בקדושתך *Hivdalta vekidashta
es amcha Yisrael bikdushasecha* and then ותתן לנו ה' אלוהינו *Vatiten lanu
Hashem Elokeinu*. So they basically which is our נוסח *nusach* of what
we do when יום טוב *Yom Tov* says when יום טוב *Yom
Tov* comes on מוצאי שבת *Motza'ei Shabbos*. So what we do basically
is we incorporate it into the ברכה *beracha* of מקדש ישראל והזמנים
*mekadesh Yisrael vehazmanim*, which is actually interesting, right? Because that's the ברכה
*beracha* of קדושת יום טוב *kedushas Yom Tov* and that's the ברכה
*beracha* where you're incorporating the separation between also שבת *Shabbos* and יום
טוב *Yom Tov*, but obviously you can't call it חול *chol*, so
we're calling it, you know, בין קדושת שבת לקדושת יום טוב *bein
kedushas
Shabbos
likedushas Yom Tov* and this is an עיקר *ikkar*. What? And this
all right and exactly, and the end of the סיכום *sikum* for
the קידוש *Kiddush*. Okay, so that is the conclusion of that. By
the way, we should note that according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*,
it's consistent with our idea that we say it as the first
ברכה *beracha* after the three, even on you know, even in this
case although this is the central ברכה *beracha*. Let's take a look
at the next משנה Mishnah *mishna*. That's the end of about these
insertions. האומר על קן ציפור al kan tzipor? יגיעו רחמיך *Ha'omer al
kan tzippor yagi'u rachamecha*. This is a very famous משנה *mishna* that
we just read the פרשה *parsha* in the תורה Torah *Torah* about
the sending away the mother bird. If somebody says on the your
God, your compassion took coast all the way to the bird's nest
that you tell us to send away the mother bird. ועל טוב
יזכר שמך V'al tov yizacher shemecha, *Ve'al tov yizacher shemecha* and your
name will be remembered for good. מודים מודים *Modim Modim* or says
מודים *Modim* twice, משתקין אותו meshatkin oso. *meshashtikin oso*, you silence the
person. It's maybe there's somebody who's leading the דאוונען *davening* for everybody,
maybe this is somebody you just hear the guy next to you
say this, maybe it's somebody that's doing you know, what's the context
by the way that people are ad libbing, you know, and saying
this type of thing? ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* actually has a case where
somebody maybe inserts it in the תרגום targum. *Targum* when they're translating
certain פסוקים pesukim, *pesukim*. I'll talk about that in a minute. But
exactly the context of where somebody is making these declarations is not
clear. It could be the שליח ציבור sheliach tzibbur, *shliach tzibbur*, it
could be others, but somehow this is unacceptable and we have to
silence it. Now let's find out what's unacceptable about this. By the
way, I should point out because the general theme we've been dealing
with is... In the תרגום when they're translating certain פסוקים, psukim I'll
talk about that in a minute. But exactly the context of where
somebody is making these declarations is not clear. It could be the
שליח ציבור, sheliach tzibbur? could be others, but somehow this is unacceptable
and we have to silence it. Now let's find out what's unacceptable
about this. By the way, I should point out because the general
theme we've been dealing with is like I said, personal כוונה kavanah
and fixed nature of תפילה, tefillah, so that's a general tension, but
here also it speaks, sometimes if you allow your personal sort of,
you compose your own text, you could be saying wrong things, inappropriate,
theologically incorrect things. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about
this. בישלמא מודים מודים משתקין אותו, Bishlama modim modim meshatkin oso, I
understand if somebody says מודים twice we silence him משום דמחזי כשתי
רשויות, mishum d'mechzei k'shtei reshuyos, it looks like there are
two divinities and they're definitely in a Zoroastrian context, which was one
that had two divinities, so maybe you're giving acknowledgment to both, so
that's very problematic even if it wasn't your
intent, we don't want to allow those types of things. ועל טוב
יזכר שמך, your name shall be remembered for good, for good things,
so
נמי, nami, it sounds like we only praise God and acknowledge God
for good things and not for bad things. ותנן, V'tnan, and we
taught, חייב אדם לברך על הרעה כשם שמברך על הטובה, chayav adam
l'varech al hara k'shem shemivarech al hatov, that you have to bless
God even for the bad as much as you do for the
good, and we'll discuss that later when it appears in a משנה
later on. So those I understand what is sort of theologically problematic
about those statements. אלא, על קן ציפור יגיעו רחמיך, Ela, al kan
tzipor yagi'u rachamecha, your compassion goes to the bird's nest, מאי טעמא,
mai ta'ama, what's the problem with that? It's a very nice thing,
God's compassion goes to the bird. פליגי בה תרי אמוראי במערבא, Pligi
ba trei amora'ei b'Ma'arava, two אמוראי amora'ei argued in the West, in
מערבא. Ma'arava. רבי יוסי בר אבין ורבי יוסי בר זבידא, Rabbi Yose
bar Abin v'Rabbi Yose bar Zvida, two רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yoses, רבי
יוסי בר אבין ורבי יוסי בר זבידא. Rabbi Yose bar Abin and
Rabbi Yose bar Zvida. חד אמר מפני שמטיל קנאה במעשה בראשית, Chad
amar mipnei shematil kinah b'ma'aseh bereishis, one said because it
puts jealousy amongst God's creatures. Oh, you're nice to the birds, but
what about the other animals? וחד אמר מפני שעושה מידותיו של הקדוש
ברוך הוא רחמים ואינם אלא גזירות, V'chad amar mipnei she'oseh midosav shel
Hakadosh Baruch Hu rachamim v'einam ela gezeiros, it makes God's attributes compassion
and they're just no more than edicts. I'll discuss that, let's just
finish this and then I'll go back and discuss that. ההוא דנחית
קמיה דרבה, Hahu d'nechis kamei d'Rabba, a certain person went in front
of רבה Rabba and here the גמרא makes it very clear at
least in this case that the context was leading שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh
Esrei, went down to lead the prayers, ואמר, v'amar, and said 'אתה
חסת על קן ציפור, Atah chasta al kan tzipor, you God had
compassion on the bird's nest, אתה חוס ורחם עלינו, atah chus v'rachem
aleinu, you should have compassion on us.' Again, makes it an interesting
lesson. Where's he saying this? Where's he ad libbing in דאוונינג davening
if he's the שליח ציבור? shliach tzibur So maybe he was, maybe
you could say in שמע קולינו, Shma Koleinu, maybe it was a
תחנון, Tachanun, again the interesting question of where do you have the
opportunity to add things. Anyway, אמר רבה, amar Rabba, so רבה Rabba
said, כמה ידעי האי צורבא מרבנן לרצויי למאריה, kama yadei hai tzurba
m'rabanan l'ratzuyei l'marei, oh, how great, how much, see how much this
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham knows how to appease his Creator. Look at
the beautiful דאוונינג davening he's doing. He meant it sarcastic. Yeah, he
could have meant it sarcastic. Oh, what a really beautiful
דאוונינג. davening. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said, והמשתקין
אותו תנן, v'hamishatkin oso tnan, how can you say that when it
just says you silence him? So the גמרא says, רבה נמי לחדודי
לאביי הוא דבעי, Rabba nami l'chadudei l'Abaye hu d'ba'ei, רבה Rabba was
also basically testing אביי Abaye to see if אביי Abaye picked up
what was the problem with it. Did you see that דאוונינג, davening,
well what do you think about that דאוונינג? davening? Anyway, so now
what is the problem here about על קן ציפור? al kan tzipor
That עושה מידותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא רחמים
ואינם אלא גזירות.
oseh midosav shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu rachamim
v'einam ela gezeiros.
Why? So anyway, what's so bad? I mean shouldn't we say that
this is an expression of God's compassion?
So both, there's a whole approach. I actually read about this this
שבת in the שבתתין. Shabsatin. There's a whole issue about טעמי המצוות,
Ta'amei HaMitzvos, looking for the reasons behind מצוות. mitzvos. How do we
see מצוות mitzvos as expressions of תורה Torah values? And that's an
important question because presumably if they are expressions of תורה Torah values,
we should be trying to live our lives according to those values
even when it's not in the context of מצוות. mitzvos. Which is
why there's a serious endeavor of looking for
טעמי המצוות, Ta'amei HaMitzvos, for over a thousand years it's been a
little Jewish cottage industry, so maybe for 2,000 years. So
here it says, oh no, you shouldn't say it's compassion, it's just
גזירות. gezeiros. And רש"י Rashi says here and this appears in מגילה
Megilla as well, basically yeah, פשט, p'shat, you're supposed to treat God's
commandments even ones like קן ציפור kan tzipor as just about obedience.
The only thing that we want from מצוות mitzvos is obedience and
that's how you treat them and you're not supposed to look for
reasons or for values or whatever. It's about God said it, you
do it, that's the entire value that that achieves is the value
of obedience. But רמב"ם Rambam and רמב"ן Ramban both don't like that
because they both think that there's a difference between what at the
end of the day we should do it because God said so,
but that doesn't mean that we should not try to find an
expression of values as well. So how do you deal with this
position? So the רמב"ם Rambam so רמב"ן Ramban reinterprets it. He says
the problem is is that it makes it as though God cares
about animals. And maybe that's not what the reason is. Maybe it's
not that God cares about animals, God cares about us, that we
should be people of
compassion. And therefore, don't act this way to animals not because you
God care about not because God directly cares about animal suffering, but
because he cares about how our actions will create within us senses
of compassion or cruelty. what it does to us. So he reads
גזירות gezeirot is that a גזירה gezeirah means something that I, an
edict that I pass because I care about my subjects. So it's
not that God is רחמן rachaman on the bird, it's גזירות gezeirot
because God cares about us. It's a little bit of a stretch.
But that's what the רמב"ם Rambam says. רמב"ן Ramban says, okay, there's
an opinion here that says that. We don't פוסקן posken that way.
Fine. There is an opinion that says it's all about obedience and
nothing else, but we reject that opinion and the רמב"ן Ramban says
all of us believe, you know, that we should look at God's
מצוות mitzvot as seeing them as an expression of certain values and
those are values that should also transcend and not be limited just
to the observance of those מצוות. mitzvot. So this is a very
important text for the issues about what do you call it? About
טעמי
המצוות. ta'amei hamitzvot. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi interestingly has a version of this
that says, you know, question is where was this inserted in דאוונינג?
davening? The ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that somebody was doing a תרגום. You
know, they had a side-by-side Aramaic translation of the תורה Torah. when
they were reading it. And when they got to the פסוק pasuk
about שור או כשב או עז וכי יולד ושור ואת בנו לא
תשחטו ביום אחד, shor o chesev o ez ki yivaled veshor ve'et
beno lo tishchatu beyom echad, which is very similar, right, not to
kill the mother and the child the same day. They translated it
as, you know, whatever, a sheep or whatever, You God should have
compassion on us like You had compassion on the, you know, sheep
and the whatever and things. And then שור או כשב או עז
ושור ואת בנו לא תשחטו ביום אחד. shor o chesev o ez
veshor ve'et beno lo tishchatu beyom echad. They just like inserted a
little line in the middle of their translation, a little prayer. And
it said similarly, ah, can't do that, you know, because this is
making it רחמים rachamim and it's not necessarily about רחמים. rachamim. It
had a similar opinion. There now what about one other word about
the other opinion, which is that you're making קנאה במעשה בראשית kinah
bema'aseh bereishit jealousy מעשה בראשית. ma'aseh bereishit. What does that mean? So
in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it doesn't have that. What it has is
it's like you're actually complaining to God, and maybe you could read
this in the בבלי Bavli as well. You're saying, God, look, You
had compassion on the mother bird. Why don't You have compassion on
me? Why is it, why do I have it bad? Okay, now
that's interesting because just last two days we were reading about models
of תפילה tefillah of משה Moshe and חנה Channah that they were
a little challenging God. But the ירושלמי says that that would be
inappropriate. That's like to complaining and finding fault with God and maybe
that's what's going on here. What I would say is I would
read my take on this is the following is that you could
read both opinions as taking two sides, two extremes on the question
of טעמי המצוות. ta'amei hamitzvot. Because the concern of טעמי המצוות ta'amei
hamitzvot is when you say, here's the value that's being expressed by
these מצוות, mitzvot, then you say, okay, then it really doesn't matter
if I do this מצווה mitzvah or not do the מצווה. mitzvah.
What really matters is the value that's behind it. And that טעמי
המצוות ta'amei hamitzvot could sometimes undermine that sense of obligation, that גזירה
gezeirah aspect. So there's a debate how do you look at this.
So one person says, I'm very concerned that any discussion of טעמי
המצוות ta'amei hamitzvot is going to undermine the sense of obligation. I
don't want you talking about it. It's just גזירה gezeirah and not
רחמים. rachamim. The other might position might be saying it's the opposite,
is that the problem wasn't that he dealt with טעמי המצוות, ta'amei
hamitzvot, that he found the value. The problem was that this person
defined the value too narrowly. You defined the value as God cares
about birds. God doesn't just care about birds, God cares about all
creatures. You're עושה קנאה במעשה בראשית oseh kinah bema'aseh bereishit in the
sense that you are too narrow in how you are defining this
value of the תורה. Torah And therefore, you know, so you could
see the two opinions as debating when you deal with טעמי המצוות,
ta'amei hamitzvot, is the problem that you went too far or not
far enough, and those are the two opinions being expressed here. Okay,
let's just finish a little bit into the two
דף daf or see if we can make the bottom page. All
right, let's, yeah, let's get totally being caught up. We got a
few more minutes. So the גמרא says like this. ההוא דנחית קמיה
דרבי
חנינא, Hahu denachis kamei d'Rabbi Chanina,
somebody went down to lead שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei in front of
רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, אמר, he said in the דאוונינג, davening, and
here was also adds an opinion which again you see is that
there was a certain amount of latitude even at this time about
the exact text, and here's what he said when he was leading
the שמונה עשרה: Shemoneh Esrei: האל הגדול הגבור והנורא והאדיר והעזוז והיראוי
והחזק והאמיץ והודאי והנכבד, Ha'el Hagadol Hagibor Vehanora Veha'adir Veha'azuz Veha'yirui Veha'chazak
Veha'amitz Vehavadai Vehanichbad, etc., etc., etc.
Okay, he's going on and on and on and he's saying all
these names. המתין לו עד דסיים, Hamtin lo ad desayam, he waited
until he got through the whole that all of that list, סיימה
siyama and when he finished, maybe also when he finished the whole
דאוונינג davening and was now he could talk to him, אמר ליה,
amar lei, or but maybe it sounds like even when he just
finished that list and maybe even said this in the middle of
the דאוונינג, davening, סיימתינהו לכולי שבחי דמרך? Siyamtinhu lekulei shvachei demarech?
Tell me, have you finished all of saying all of God's
praises?
So why you going on so much? למה לי כולי האי? Lama
li kulei hai? So why are you going on so much? אנן
הני תלת דאמרינן, Anan hanei telat de'amrinan, the three we say, האל
הגדול הגבור, Ha'el Hagadol Hagibor, אילמלא דאמרינהו משה רבינו באורייתא, ilmalei de'amrinhu
Moshe Rabbeinu be'Oraita, if they were not already in the
תורה when, right, ואתו אנשי כנסת הגדולה ותקנינהו בתפלה ve'atu Anshei Knesset
HaGedolah vetakninhu bitefillah and were they not established in our liturgy, לא
הוינן יכולין למימר להו, lo havinan yacholin lemimar lehu, we couldn't say
them because once you start praising God, there's no end, right? God
is infinite. It would be. no end to it. So really, you
know, this we only say what we can say because it's already
said in the Torah that this is an appropriate way to praise
God. Anything more if you're going to start ad-libbing here, then there's
no, then, you know, you have no license here. אמרת כולי האי
ואזלת amart kulei hai ve'azlat and you're going on and on. משל
למלך בשר ודם שהיו לו אלף אלפי אלפים דינרי זהב. mashal lemelech
basar vadam shehayu lo elef alfei alafim dinarei zahav. A king had
millions of gold coins. דינר dinar coins,
millions of dollars. והיו מקלסין אותו בשל כסף. vehayu mekalsin oto beshel
kesef. He said, oh, you have a lot of silver. והלא גנאי
הוא לו. vehalo genai hu lo. That is, that you know, that
that that's unbecoming. So basically it's very interesting in terms of the
tension that I keep on going back to about sort of the
personal and the adding your own text and the fixed nature. Here
it says while there might be other places that you can add,
here we only have a license in praising God and directly talking
about God's attributes to use the words that were used by Moshe
that were established in the liturgy because anything else is basically saying
I really want to say everything that God you're about and then
there's no end. So what we only are able to do is
actually to do the things that we are repeating what others said
and we're keeping to a fixed liturgy. And that's in terms of
this aspect.
Instead of creating new liturgy?
No,
only in this direct discussion of God's attributes. The whole other other
things are all an ongoing issue. But here the focus is there's
some places where they're theologically problematic like על קן ציפור or going
on and on about God, about God, you know, about describing God
and praising God directly האל הגדול הגבור. Ha'eil Hagadol Hagibor. Here's where
we're putting limits. Here's where your license is limited to what the
פסוקים use. You know, the Gemara says, uses just another phrase which
is לך דומיה תהילה. lecha dumiyah tehillah. To You God silence is
praise, like you acknowledge that there's no way you can begin to
articulate, so you have you know you rather than going on and
on, you realize that the less the better. This leads to Rambam's,
not leads to, but consistent with Rambam's whole general theology which is
called like negative theology, which is that any words used to describe
God, forget praise, you know God is infinite, any words used are
fundamentally a misrepresentation because they're human concepts and they're therefore limited. And
therefore the ultimate description of God is that we, what is that
we can't describe God. God is so much beyond the ability, which
is Rambam's negative theology. Here specifically in the context of prayer and
praise, but they're consistent ideas. Okay, let's take a look as the
Gemara continues. ואמר רבי חנינא. ve'amar Rabbi Chanina. הכל בידי שמים. hakol
biydei shamayim. So since we talked about Rabbi Chanina before, we're going
to see another one. הכל בידי שמים חוץ מיראת שמים. hakol biydei
shamayim chutz miyirat shamayim. Everything is in the hand of heaven except
fear. God choice to choose to be good or evil, that's up
to us. Everything else might be dictated like the genes we're born
with, the circumstances in life, but Godly ultimately how whether we're good
whether we fear God or not and whether we do the right
thing or not that is our choice. שנאמר ועתה ישראל מה ה'
אלהיך שואל מעמך. shene'emar ve'atah Yisrael mah Hashem Elohecha sho'el me'imach. Now
you Israel, what does God ask of you, says Moshe? כי אם
ליראה ki im leyirah only to fear God ולשמור את כל חוקותיו
velishmor et kol chukotav goes on and on and on about what
it means to live a perfect life. That's all God asks of
you? Fear Him, do all the mitzvot, do everything you're required to
do. What else? It's nothing, it's all God wants from you. So
anyway the point is God is asking you, meaning God is not
going to dictate this. This is up to you to do. Now,
now the Gemara has another comment which is similar to the other
point. אטו יראת שמים מילתא זוטרתא היא? atu yirat shamayim milta zutraita
hi? That's a small thing? What does God want? Just יראת שמים?
yirat shamayim? והאמר רבי חנינא משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. veha'amar Rabbi
Chanina mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. אין לו להקדוש ברוך הוא בבית
גנזיו. ein lo le-Hakadosh Baruch Hu beveit genazav. God has nothing in
His storehouse, His treasure house, אלא אוצר של יראת שמים. ela otzar
shel yirat shamayim. The storehouse of fear of heaven. God treasures when
people have this fear of heaven. It's such a rare thing, right?
And again especially if it's the one thing God does not control
as it were, it's something of our choice, that's extremely treasure valuable.
שנאמר יראת ה' היא אוצרו. shene'emar yirat Hashem hi otzaro.
Awe fear of God that is what is in the way it's
being read in God's storehouse. So the Gemara says so how can
Moshe make light of it? It's all God wants. So the Gemara
says אין לגבי משה מילתא זוטרתא היא. in legabei Moshe milta zutraita
hi. Yes, for Moshe's perspective it was no big deal. דאמר רבי
חנינא. de'amar Rabbi Chanina. משל לאדם שמבקשים ממנו כלי גדול ויש לו.
mashal leadam shemevakshim mimenu kli gadol veyesh lo. דומה לו ככלי קטן.
domeh lo ke-kli katan. If you ask somebody a big vessel and
they have, so for them it's nothing, no big deal. You want
to borrow my
car, you know, you know, which Cadillac do you want, you know,
you know, which of my Lexuses do you want? No big deal,
I got a dozen of them. Okay. But but if you ask
for כלי קטן ואין לו. kli katan ve'ein lo. If you ask
for something small but the person doesn't have it, דומה לו ככלי
גדול. domeh lo ke-kli gadol. Then it's like you're asking a huge
thing. So you know the thing it's there's a subjective element here
to whether it's a big deal or not a big deal based
on where the person is standing. So Moshe's saying look I did
it, shouldn't be so hard for you, it's no big deal. But
the reality is it's a very big deal and that is ultimately
you know something that is rare and very precious. Okay let's just
read till end this up. מודים מודים משתקין אותו. modim modim meshatekin
oto. Modim modim you silence
him. אמר רבי זירא. amar Rabbi Zeira. Especially, especially... So the Gemara
says ורמינהו u-reminhu הקורא את שמע וכופלה הרי זה מגונה. ha-koreh et
Shema ve-khofulah ha-rey zeh meguneh. If somebody says the שמע Shema and
repeats it, that's, you know, that's מגונה, meguneh, like despicable, that might
be a little harsh. Anyway, that's inappropriate, not inappropriate, it's too light.
Disgraceful, I don't know, something reprehensible. Okay. So the Gemara says מגונה
הוא דהוי הא משתקין לא משתקינן ליה. meguneh hu de-havey ha meshatkin
lo meshatkinan leh. It's מגונה, meguneh, but it doesn't mean we silence
him. You know, it might be inappropriate, but it doesn't mean that
we actually silence the person, let's say remove him from being שליח
ציבור or something of that nature. So the Gemara says לא קשיא
הא דאמר מילתא מילתא ותני לה והא דאמר פסוקא פסוקא ותני לה.
lo kashya ha de-amar milta milta ve-tani lah ve-ha de-amar pasuka pasuka
ve-tani lah. In one case where you said each word and repeated
it, שמע שמע ישראל ישראל. Shema Shema Yisrael Yisrael. The other is
he said a פסוק pasuk and repeated the whole פסוק. pasuk. Now
which is better, which is worse? So רשי Rashi says when you
say every word twice, then that's inappropriate, but that's not that we
silence you. That's not like you're acknowledging to two separate, you know,
divinities. שמע שמע ישראל ישראל, Shema Shema Yisrael Yisrael, it's just okay,
for some reason you're repeating
yourself. But when you say a whole פסוק, pasuk, then one פסוק
pasuk is given to one divinity and the other פסוק pasuk is
said to the other divinity, and that's the problem. So that makes
a lot of sense, although it doesn't fit the language so much,
because the language is הקורא את שמע וכופלה ha-koreh et Shema ve-khofulah
sounds like you're repeating the whole section, not just repeating each word.
תוספות Tosafot says the reverse. To say each word, that's a problem.
If you repeat the whole thing, it's not a problem. Which is,
by the way, fascinating, because there are definitely people that are a
little OCD about this stuff and we'll see that in a minute
and they're so concerned did I have enough כוונה kavanah and they'll
repeat it multiple times, you know, and that's obviously a problem. Now
of course you could repeat it later, you could wait time and
repeat it later, but in the immediate context doing it at the
same time is clearly an issue. It's either מגונה meguneh or even
worse משתקין אותו. So now the Gemara says and that
means only those parts, we're only talking about those parts.
Right, and those other parts. Now let's take a look. The Gemara
ends on that point about repeating and about being so anxious about
your כוונה. kavanah. So it says like this אמר ליה רב פפא
לאביי ודילמא מעיקרא לא כיוון דעתיה והשתא כיוון דעתיה. amar leh Rav
Papa le-Abaye ve-dilma me-ikara lo kivan dateyh ve-hashta kivan dateyh. Maybe he
felt he didn't have enough כוונה kavanah at first and now he's
doing it again, especially if it's an issue about repeating the whole
thing. Oh, I didn't have enough כוונה kavanah for that פסוק, pasuk,
I'll repeat the פסוק, pasuk, okay? Which people actually do. So אמר
ליה, amar leh, חברותא כלפי שמיא? havruta klapei shamaya? What, you're pals
with heaven? So meaning that it's, you know, that you're demonstrating that
you didn't have enough כוונה, kavanah, and that's so what were you
doing not having enough כוונה kavanah in the first time? Okay, but
I didn't! So the Gemara מי איכא, mi ika, can you be
pals with heaven to not have
כוונה? kavanah? אי לא כיוון דעתיה מעיקרא מחינן ליה במרזפתא דנפחא עד
דמכוון דעתיה. ei lo kivan dateyh me-ikara machinan leh be-marzafta de-nafcha ad
de-makhvin dateyh. We hit him with basically a
hammer of a smith, of a blacksmith, until he has כוונה. kavanah.
We beat him up. We don't accept it, which basically, by the
way, though I should say although it's a little bit exaggerated is
important because it's always an issue, you know, to how much you
encourage bad behavior by allowing this type of stuff, by allowing the
makeup. If we basically say no makeups, we're going to force you
to have more כוונה kavanah than if we give you an option
of a makeup. So he's not denying the fact that people don't
always have כוונה, kavanah, he's saying this is not the way you
deal with it. You don't repeat it. Say tough luck, you didn't
have כוונה, kavanah, you should have been, next time you'll be a
little bit better. But okay, and that's actually his approach. We will
pick up with this.